On the 7th of January 1978 an article entitled
‘Iran and Red and Black Colonisation’ appeared
in Ettela’at, an Iranian daily newspaper. It
put forward an implausible argument that the
conservative religious leaders of Iran were in
league with the Communists and were attempting
to overthrow the government of the Shah, the
royal ruler of Iran. The article is widely
understood to have been written at the behest of
the Shah and ultimately sparked the first stages
of the Iranian Revolution. Why was the Shah so
unpopular and what did he do to try to cling
to power? This is the story of Shah Mohammed
Reza Pahlavi and the White Revolution.
The man known to history as Shah Mohammad Reza
Pahlavi was born on the 26th of October 1919
in the city of Tehran in Iran. Mohammad had
a twin-sister named Ashraf. His father was
Reza Khan, though he is more widely known as
Reza Shah Pahlavi. Reza was born in 1878. He
joined the Persian military when he was 14
years old and became a rising officer in the
Persian Cossacks Brigade by his twenties. Reza
was interested in western culture and ideas and
was well connected by his mid-twenties with
the ambassadors and consuls representing the
European powers in Tehran. Reza married four
times. His second wife was Nimtaj Ayromlou,
later known as Tadj ol-Molouk. They married in
1916. Mohammad had ten siblings and half-siblings,
but he was his father’s oldest son.
When Mohammad was born in 1919, the Qajar
Dynasty was celebrating the 130th anniversary
of their rule over Iran. Persia, as the
western powers termed it, was one of the very few
countries outside of Europe and the Americas which
managed to remain independent during the first age
of globalisation in the nineteenth century and the
accelerated wave of western imperialism that came
with it. This reflected Persia’s status as a great
centre of civilization stretching back to ancient
times. The Persian Empire between the mid-sixth
and mid-fourth centuries BC had ruled from Egypt
and Turkey all the way east to Afghanistan. Later
the Persians exerted substantial influence over
the Arab Caliphates that were ruled from Baghdad,
while Safavid Persia resisted the armies of
the Ottoman Empire in the sixteenth century.
In the nineteenth century, after the establishment
of the Qajar Dynasty, the country became a focus
of geopolitical rivalry between Russia and
Britain, with Russia controlling all of
the land north of Persia and east of the Caspian
Sea, and Britain ruling over India and Pakistan.
The ‘Great Game’, as this Russo-British rivalry
in Central Asia was known, came to an end in the
1890s and 1900s through several agreements between
Russia and Britain. Persia remained independent,
but Britain did have a substantial interest in
the country, particularly after the discovery of
large petroleum reserves here and the formation
in 1909 of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company.
Although Persia had managed to remain
nominally independent under the Qajar Dynasty,
and also tried to remain neutral in the
First World War when it broke out in 1914,
the country’s geostrategic importance meant
that large parts of it were occupied between
1914 and 1918 as the British and
Russians, who were now allies,
tried to defeat the Ottoman Empire in the Middle
East. Later the country was also impacted by the
spillover effect of the Russian Revolution and
Civil War from 1917 through to the early 1920s.
All of this instability led to a terrible
famine in Iran between 1917 and 1919. This
often overlooked and forgotten event led to the
deaths of an estimated two million Iranians.
This, combined with the impact of the Spanish
Flu pandemic at the same time, and the way in
which the Qajar Dynasty had been damaged by the
occupation of the country during the war, led to
a military coup in Persia on the 22nd of February
1921. This was led by Mohammad’s father, with
clandestine British support. Reza Khan then became
the Minister of War and spent the next two years
quelling numerous local rebellions across Persia.
In 1923 he assumed the office of Prime Minister.
Finally, on the 15th of December 1925, the Qajar
Dynasty, which had been left in place after the
coup of 1921, were removed entirely and Reza Khan
ascended as the new Shah or king of Persia, with
the dynastic name Pahlavi. Ten years later, in
1935, he began issuing directives that henceforth
the nation was to be known as Iran rather than
Persia, the latter of which is actually a Greek
exonym for the entire Persian Empire rather
than the local name for the country.
Mohammad would barely have been aware of the
turmoil which surrounded him throughout his youth.
He was born into a country suffering through civil
war, disease and famine, and grew up surrounded by
military coups and political scheming that his
father was at the heart of. He had only recently
celebrated his sixth birthday when his father
became Shah, an event which saw Mohammad become
the Crown Prince of Iran. His status meant that
his education was overseen closely by his father,
who enlisted military officers as his tutors.
Although Reza had no major experience of Europe
himself, he was aware of the need to modernise
Iran, and so he sent Mohammad off to attend a
boarding school in Switzerland, the Institut le
Rosey. This was in 1931, when he was nearing his
twelfth birthday. Clearly, he arrived in Europe
with an elevated sense of himself as Crown Prince,
but his years here were formative. Mohammad
developed a love of French culture and learned to
speak several European languages. In later years
he and his third wife spoke with their children in
French at home. His later modernisation programme
in Iran was partly due to his experiences during
his teenage years in Europe. He returned home in
1936 to enter the Military Academy in Tehran. By
then it was clear that the world was becoming more
militaristic and violent again. Nazi Germany was
rearming speedily after breaching the terms of
the Treaty of Versailles and would soon annex
Austria and then Czechoslovakia in Europe. Italy
conquered Abyssinia via the Second Italo-Ethiopian
War of 1935 to 1937, and Japan expanded
its plans to conquer China in 1937, having
previously annexed Korea and created the puppet
state of Manchukuo in Manchuria. The outbreak of
the Second World War in September 1939 after
Germany invaded Poland would lead to Mohammad
becoming Shah of Iran sooner than expected.
Mohammad’s father adopted a policy of neutrality
following the outbreak of the war. However, over
time, Iran was dragged into the conflict more and
more. It was strategically important because
of its oil supplies, which Nazi Germany was
anxious to acquire, and it also became central
to Britain’s campaign to supply the Soviet Union
after the Germans invaded the USSR in the summer
of 1941. Within days of the commencement of the
war between the Soviets and the Nazis, there were
discussions in London, Moscow and Berlin about the
strategic necessity of securing control over Iran
for both sides. The Germans were hoping to pull
Mohammad’s father into the Axis alliance, but the
Soviets and British acted decisively before they
could do so. They felt they needed to act as
Reza had adopted an increasingly independent
position in the 1930s and was anxious to break
away from British and Russian influence in Central
Asia and the Middle East. Fearing that he might
ally with Germany, on the 25th of August 1941 a
join Anglo-Soviet campaign was launched to invade
Iran and take over the country’s key apparatus. A
ceasefire was agreed to, five days later, and the
Iranian army collapsed in the face of the Allied
invasion. Reza Khan was sent a polite message by
the British two weeks later instructing him to
kindly abdicate in favour of his son. The British
had briefly considered whether it would be best to
reinstall the Qajar Dynasty that Reza had removed
from power back in 1925, but in the end, they
decided that maintaining the Pahlavi Dynasty was
as satisfactory, if Mohammad proved to be biddable
for so long as the war was underway. Reza had no
option except to do as instructed, which meant
that on the 16th of September 1941, six weeks
before his 22nd birthday, Mohammad became the
Shah of Iran. His father went into exile and died
in Johannesburg in South Africa in July 1944.
The new, young Shah in Tehran had no independence
of action in the first years of his reign. Iran
had effectively been occupied by the Allied Powers
and remained under Allied occupation until the war
ended. Iran was even host to the first major
meeting of the ‘Big Three’ Allied leaders,
the British Prime Minister, Winston Churchill,
the Soviet dictator, Joseph Stalin, and the US
President, Franklin Delano Roosevelt, between the
28th of November and the 1st of December 1943.
While the Shah was involved in a ceremonial
capacity in the governance of Iran between
September 1941 and the end of the war in 1945,
the real rulers of the country were the British
and Soviet ambassadors and their staff. Ahmad
Qavam, an Iranian politician who had served
as Prime Minister back in the early 1920s after
the coup of 1921, returned to the office of Prime
Minister during the war and was actually more
influential than the young Shah. Mohammad grew
to resent Qavam’s power. The shift in the power
dynamic between them only started once the war
ended in Europe in May 1945. A crisis erupted in
the Middle East after Stalin was slow to withdraw
the Red Army from Iranian territory. A prolonged
dispute over the border region between Iran and
Azerbaijan provided the opportunity for the Shah
to push Qavam out of the office of Prime Minister
and to assert his own position as ruler of
the country. Thus, from late 1947 onwards,
the Shah began to transition from a puppet ruler
of a militarily-occupied country to an independent
ruler of a post-war sovereign nation.
This capacity for asserting his independence
was reflected in the Shah’s personal life.
Shortly after he returned to Iran from Europe,
back in 1936, his father had entered negotiations
with the Egyptian royal family to organise a
dynastic alliance between Egypt and Iran
by marrying Mohammad to Princess Fawzia,
the daughter of King Fuad I of Egypt and sister of
King Farouk I who ascended to the throne in 1936.
From a dynastic perspective this was an excellent
alliance for the upstart Pahlavi Dynasty,
which was looking to cement its place among
the royal houses of the Middle East, but it
was not a happy marriage. They had a daughter
together in 1940, Princess Shahnaz, following
which they became increasingly estranged. Once
the war began to wind down in Allied victory,
Fawzia returned to Egypt, where she obtained a
divorce under Egyptian law. The Shah obtained
a separate Iranian divorce in 1948. He then
married Soraya Esfandiary-Bakhtiary in 1951.
This second marriage ended in divorce too in 1958
after the union failed to result in any children.
The Shah needed a legitimate male heir to continue
the dynastic line and so he divorced Soraya and
married Farah Diba in 1959. This third marriage
produced four children, two boys, Reza and Ali,
and two daughters, Farahnaz and Leila. The claim
that the Shah was possibly gay, based on his
very close friendship with the Swiss man, Ernest
Perron, has been put forward in several studies.
They met while the Shah was studying in
Switzerland in his teenage years and Perron
became a powerful courtier and official in Iran
after the war. While Perron was clearly gay,
and the position he obtained in Iran based on
his close relationship with the Shah was unusual,
there is no concrete evidence to imply
the Shah was gay or bisexual.
Perron fell from power at the Shah’s court owing
to his role in the Abadan Crisis. This was the
name given to the general period of crisis in
Iran’s politics between 1951 and 1954. Abadan
was the centre of the oil-extraction industry
in the country. The crisis was sparked by the
assassination on the 7th of March 1951 of the
Iranian Prime Minister, Haj Ali Razmara, by an
Islamic fundamentalist. Although this foreshadowed
later clashes between conservative religious
elements in Iran and the Shah’s government,
the immediate cause of the assassination was
a widespread belief that Razmara was about to
sign an unfavourable deal with the British that
would extend the rights of the Anglo-Iranian
Oil Company in the country, which was perceived
as a legacy of the European age of imperialism.
Razmara was succeeded by Mohammad Mossadegh. As
Prime Minister he was the driving force behind the
nationalisation of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company.
This in turn created two years of tensions as the
British argued to their American allies that the
nationalisation of the oil industry was a sign
that Iran was about to fall into the Soviet,
communist camp in the intensifying Cold War.
Although it is very doubtful that this was likely,
British resentments ultimately resulted in a
western-backed coup in August 1953. While it was
occurring the Shah fled Iran, flying to Europe. He
remained in Rome until the unrest had died down,
spending much of his time in the nightclubs
of the Italian capital and waiting to see what
would happen back home. Even supporters of the
Shah condemned his flight to Europe as an act
of cowardice, but when he returned to Iran his
position was stronger than it had ever been,
as the western powers were content to have a
strong Shah in Iran who would act as a bulwark
against the growing pan-Arabism elsewhere in
the Middle East, which had a socialist ideology
and leaned more towards Moscow on account of
Washington’s support for the state of Israel.
The Shah became a much more authoritarian ruler
following his restoration. It must be admitted
that he was overseeing a country that was very
difficult to rule. Iran is often viewed as a
homogenous state, but it is actually a patchwork
of different ethnic and religious groups,
with the Balochs in the southeast and the
Azeris and Kurds in the northwest all being
inclined towards regional separatism. On top of
this, the more secular policies which the Shah,
and his father before him, favoured had brought
the Pahlavi Dynasty into conflict with the
conservative religious leaders of the country
as early as the 1930s. Add to this the tensions
created by the crisis of the early 1950s and the
experience of having to flee the country in 1953,
and the Shah was consequently inclined to adopt
a more authoritarian approach by the mid-1950s.
Press censorship and the monitoring of religious
groups and leaders became commonplace. Then,
in 1957, the Bureau for Intelligence and Security
of the State, better known by its acronym, SAVAK,
was set up. This secret police force expanded
through the late 1950s and 1960s to become a
small, secretive army with thousands of members.
It has been observed by many commentators that the
Shah’s SAVAK paved the way for later militias
and secret police forces established by the
Islamic Republic of Iran. While there is no
denying that SAVAK was a brutal regime that
killed thousands of people and detained
and tortured many others over 22 years,
its activities pale in comparison to the murder
and illegal detention of hundreds of thousands
of people by modern Iranian security services
such as the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps.
Nevertheless, SAVAK’s conduct remains a black mark
on the record of the Shah as ruler of Iran.
In 1963 the Shah began a programme of
modernisation known as the White Revolution.
This was not entirely novel. All the way back
in the 1930s, his father had begun introducing
measures to orientate Iran towards becoming a more
western-style country. For instance, industrial
advisors were brought in to begin setting up
factories and providing technical knowledge for
new Iranian businesses and companies. There was
also a drive to break down the traditional pillars
of Iranian society, religion and the social
hierarchy that went back hundreds of years.
As a Francophile who was educated in Europe,
the Shah wanted to go even further. In 1963,
a referendum was put to the Iranian people to
commence a sweeping range of reforms. It passed
in a landslide, primarily because it was boycotted
by those who opposed the proposed reforms. Thus,
over the next fifteen years, under the auspices
of the White Revolution, huge amounts of land that
belonged to the traditional aristocracy, tribal
chiefs and the powerful Shia Muslim clerics was
taken into state ownership and then redistributed
to farmers and the lower-middle class. There was
also a very considerable investment of Iran’s oil
revenue into expanding the education system and
improving the country’s infrastructure. Literacy
levels improved markedly. In the 1950s only 15% of
Iranians were literate but by the end of the 1970s
nearly 50% of the population could read and write.
There were political reforms too. Women were given
the right to vote in Iranian elections at the
start of the White Revolution. Healthcare access
was expanded. A Health Corps was set up which
trained around 4,500 groups of medical officials
to offer local healthcare around Iran.
As positive as many of the outcomes from the
White Revolution were, the reforms were opposed
by a conservative element in Iranian society.
Iran is a complex country. On the one hand,
its sophisticated culture and history going back
to ancient times has made it a learned society and
one of the most liberal in the entire Middle East.
On the other hand, there is a strong conservative,
ultra-religious element. That duality exists in
Iran in the early twenty-first century and was
there too in the Shah’s time. In the 1960s,
the closest thing which the conservative,
religious faction had to a leader was Ayatollah
Ruhollah Khomeini, a senior Twelver Shia cleric.
The opposition which the Shah’s reforms of 1963
created turned Khomeini into a national figure.
In January 1963, when the White Revolution
started, Khomeini began giving speeches around
Iran in which he denounced the Shah and condemned
the reforms which were being initiated. He also
led the boycott of the referendum which the
Shah called on the reform programme. Then, on
the 3rd of June, Khomeini compared the Shah to the
Caliph Yazid, an early ruler of the Arab Caliphate
back in the seventh century, who played a role in
the split within the Muslim world into Sunni and
Shiite camps. Khomeini was basically saying that
the Shah was a divisive figure who was splitting
Iran into two camps through his aggressive
modernisation. The comparison also questioned
the Shah’s legitimacy as ruler of Iran. The Shah
ordered Khomeini to be arrested two days later,
a move which led to major protests and riots in
which around 400 people were killed. Khomeini was
placed under house arrest. When he was released,
he returned to giving provocative speeches against
the Shah and in the end he was arrested again and
banished in November 1964 when he was placed on a
flight to Turkey. He quickly relocated to Iraq and
spent the next thirteen years based in the city of
Najaf there, becoming a focus of opposition to
the Shah just over Iran’s western border.
The growing schism between conservative
religious forces in Iran and a more secular,
liberal community that looked towards the
west was exacerbated by the economic growth
of Iran. It is a basic fact of modern politics
that leaders can bring a certain part of their
population along with them if there is economic
growth in their country. The reforms overseen by
the Shah’s government ushered in the greatest
period of economic growth in Iranian history.
GDP growth in the 1960s and 1970s averaged
nearly 10% per year. Without a doubt,
this was based to a considerable degree on oil
revenue, especially after the 1973 Oil Crisis,
when the average cost of a barrel of oil on the
international markets quadrupled in the space
of six months from October 1973 onwards. But oil
revenue does not always lead to national economic
growth if the profits are mismanaged. The Shah’s
government oversaw an intelligent re-investment of
oil revenue to develop other parts of the economy
such as the production of textiles, cement,
petrochemicals, fertilisers, and cash crops
like sugar, dates and pistachios. In this way,
Iran set an early template for economic
diversification from oil revenue that was
subsequently adopted by the Gulf States and Saudi
Arabia. Living standards jumped. A better-educated
and more affluent cohort emerged in Iran’s cities
who dressed like they lived in Paris or Rome, went
to the cinema to watch western-produced films and
acted very differently to how their contemporaries
did in places like Saudi Arabia in the 1960s and
1970s. Underneath all of this economic change,
though, was a society that was divided over the
White Revolution for a multitude of reasons.
In the short term, this new prosperity led to
a growing centralisation of power at the royal
court, where the Shah had an increasingly
elevated sense of his own self-importance.
Beginning in the mid-1960s he started to grant
himself a series of evermore elaborate titles,
which is rarely a good sign of things to come in
an autocratic state. For instance, on the 15th of
September 1965 the announcement came that the
Shah would be known as Aryamehr, a word which
means ‘Light of the Aryans’, a reference to the
pseudo-scientific view that the vast array of
people who speak Indo-European languages, from
England all the way east to Iran and India,
are descended from a root ‘Aryan’ people. The
Shah also held the title of Bozorg Arteshtaran,
meaning ‘Great Army Leader’. In 1967, not content
with being a king, he proclaimed that he was now
Shahanshah, which means ‘King of Kings’. The
elevation of his title was accompanied by a new
formal coronation on the 26th of October that
year. Finally, in mid-October 1971, the Shah
presided over the 2500-year celebrations of the
founding of the Persian Empire in ancient times by
Cyrus the Great. These festivities were held over
a week in a tent city erected at Persepolis, which
was attended by heads of state from abroad and
other royal families. The dating was questionable.
Cyrus the Great had conquered the Babylonian
Empire in 539 BC, so it would have made more
sense to hold this 2500-year anniversary in 1961.
Ultimately it, along with his expanding array of
titles, was a sign of the Shah’s accelerating
sense of his own importance and power.
There was also an evolving foreign policy adopted
by the Shah in the 1960s and 1970s. The Pahlavi
Dynasty’s foreign relations had shifted
repeatedly. The desire to break away from
British dominance of the oil industry in the
Middle East had led to some scepticism about
western influences in Iran, which peaked in the
Abadan Crisis and the coup of 1953. Despite later
interpretations of the Shah as being a classic
Cold War-era strongman aligned with Washington,
the relationship was more complex. The US
and British intervention in 1953 led to a
new arrangement whereby Iran’s oil industry
was placed into a trust controlled by various
international entities. Because of this, the Shah
and his government were tied to the western powers
for the next 19 years but he demonstrated his
independence of action in March 1973 when he
nationalised all foreign oil interests, nullifying
the actions of the British and Americans twenty
years earlier. Although Saudi Arabia led the
oil embargo on western nations later that year,
Iran benefited greatly from the pursuant price
increase. In terms of his diplomatic stances
throughout the Middle East, the Shah adopted a
much more conciliatory line towards Israel than
the vast majority of other Muslim nations. This
was in return for US support in Iran’s regional
rivalry with Iraq. More broadly, as his reign
went on, he cultivated strong ties to the US,
Britain and France, particularly with leaders
like Charles de Gaulle in France and the US
President Richard Nixon.
Part of the Shah’s foreign policy outlook
was shaped by a desire for energy diversification
and military power in the Middle East and Central
Asia. The 1950s, 1960s and 1970s were an era
in which nuclear power was a favoured source
of energy production. The Shah’s government began
developing a nuclear programme in the late 1950s
with technical advice from the Americans, French
and West Germans. In 1967 the Tehran Research
Reactor became operational. Like so many other
nations of the era, as soon as enriched uranium
was present in the country for the purposes of
producing domestic energy, thoughts turned to
how to produce a nuclear weapon. By 1974 the US
State Department was concerned that the Iranians
were looking to use enriched plutonium to
manufacture one. They were also anxious
about the proliferation of nuclear material
around the country and concerns were expressed
in Washington about what might happen to these
resources if Iran experienced a new revolution,
invasion or change of government.
It was understandable that the administrations
of both President Gerald Ford and President
Jimmy Carter were concerned about this.
The Shah started behaving from 1974 onwards
in ways that led to rising unrest in Iran.
This is surprising on some level. Rapidly rising
oil revenue and the nationalisation of foreign
interests in the oil industry in 1973 meant that
the coffers of the Shah’s government were never
fuller but the unprecedented amount of money
at his disposal led to hubris. In March 1975,
Mohammad turned Iran into a one-party state
when he set up the new Rastakhiz Party,
or ‘Resurrection’ Party, and made it the
sole legal political party in the country,
merging multiple existing political parties into
it. More worryingly, rampant corruption developed.
Billions of dollars’ worth of oil revenue
were siphoned off into the hands of the Shah,
his family and a close coterie of aristocrats
and politicians. This uneven distribution of
Iran’s newfound wealth was compounded by steeply
rising inflation as money poured into the country
without proper fiscal management. Inflation rose
to an average of about 15% per year in the second
half of the 1970s. Corruption seeped into everyday
life, with government officials, police and court
officers all requiring bribes to serve the public
interest. Opposition to the regime spiralled
amongst both left-wing, secular liberals and much
more conservative religious leaders who looked to
Ayatollah Khomeini in exile across the border in
Iraq as a leader of their movement.
The Iranian Revolution began with the
publication of the article ‘Iran and
Red and Black Colonisation’ in Ettela’at
in January 1978, most likely at the behest
of the Shah. It escalated incrementally over
the next year. The deaths of an estimated 450
people in the Cinema Rex Fire on the 19th
of August 1978 was a major turning point.
The Shah did try to respond as opposition
demonstrations intensified around the country,
drawing hundreds of thousands of people out
onto the streets. For instance, in October
1978 the Shah announced the dissolution of the
short-lived Rastakhiz Party, hoping that political
liberalisation would quell the unrest. He also
pressured the Iraqi government to expel Khomeini.
The Ayatollah briefly resettled in France and
waited for the opportune moment to return to Iran.
These measures were ineffective and unprecedented
rallies in December 1978 led to upwards of ten
million people taking to the streets to show their
dislike of the regime and signal the need for
change. By then the Shah was becoming increasingly
desperate and paranoid. He attacked British and
US diplomats in Tehran and claimed they were
clandestinely supporting the protestors in
the hope of displacing him. Once street fighting
commenced between the government and protestors,
the regime was on borrowed time. Word soon reached
Mohammad that leading generals were in discussions
with the opposition. On the 16th of January 1979,
the Shah flew out of Iran, never to return. Two
weeks later, on the 1st of February, the Ayatollah
arrived home after fifteen years in exile. Intense
debates over the future trajectory of the country
followed and it was only in December that the
Ayatollah was confirmed as the first Supreme
Leader of the new Islamic Republic of Iran.
The narrative will always be that the Shah
fled from Iran as the opposition to his rule
reached a crescendo and he was in danger of being
overthrown and detained if he didn’t leave the
country in January 1979. In this light, the cover
story that the Shah was ill and was travelling
abroad for health reasons is seen as a smokescreen
however two things can be right at the same time.
The Shah was genuinely very ill. He had been
suffering from chronic lymphocytic leukaemia since
around 1974, a type of blood cancer. By the time
he went into exile for the second time in 1979,
his condition had sharply deteriorated. Indeed,
western leaders perhaps did not back him as
strongly as they otherwise might have because they
believed he would not live much longer. What he
did after leaving Iran was therefore unwise.
Instead of immediately seeking out the best
healthcare he could, which the family certainly
had the finances to do, he spent months travelling
across North Africa and then to Central America.
Mohammad spent time in Egypt, Morocco, Panama and
Mexico. When he was finally examined in Mexico by
a high-level physician, Dr. Benjamin Kean, things
were drastic. He had developed severe gallstones
and had multiple tumours. At that stage, President
Jimmy Carter was convinced to allow the Shah to
enter the US on compassionate grounds. Carter
had previously been reluctant to do anything that
might look like he was granting the Shah political
asylum in the US. He was receiving treatment in
America by October 1979, but surgery revealed
the extent to which his cancer had progressed
and showed that his condition was now terminal.
In early 1980 his health continued to decline as
infections set in. Undeterred, the Shah continued
to travel, returning to Egypt. He ultimately
died in Cairo on the 27th of July 1980 at 60
years of age. With the family unable to bury
him back in Iran, his remains were laid to rest
in the Al Rifa’i Mosque in Cairo in Egypt.
Iran has gone through peaks and mostly valleys
since the Shah’s time as ruler of the country.
The relationship between Iran and the western
powers collapsed after the Revolution owing
to the kidnapping of 66 Americans by Islamic
extremists with connections to the government at
the US embassy in Tehran on the 4th of November
1979. Over fifty of these were held hostage for
nearly 15 months. By the time the hostage crisis
ended in January 1981, the relationship between
Iran and the US was hostile. It never recovered.
The US supported Saddam Hussein and the Baathists
in the Iran-Iraq War that ran from 1980 to 1988,
although there was a peculiar underhand attempt
to supply Iran with weapons via the Iran-Contra
affair in the mid-1980s. The Ayatollah died
in 1989 and was succeeded by Ayatollah Ali
Khamenei as the Second Supreme Leader of Iran.
Under his rule there was a window in which Iran
could have changed course. Between 1997 and 2005
the Prime Minister, Mohammad Khatami, led a reform
movement. The turning point came in the mid-2000s
as the Ayatollah and the mullahs clamped down on
the reform movement. Ever since then there have
been protests against the regime every few years,
notably in 2009, 2017, 2023 and 2026. To cement
the position of the religious authorities,
the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps and other
security forces were expanded to include hundreds
of thousands of personnel. Meanwhile, on the
international front, Iran remained under heavy
sanctions which reduced the amount of income
it could receive from the sale of its oil,
while Iran’s support for Hezbollah in Lebanon and
the Houthis in Yemen, along with other regional
proxies, made it a constant enemy of Israel.
The US stance towards the country fluctuated,
though there was unanimity that Iran could not
be allowed to acquire a nuclear weapon.
As this torturous relationship between Iran
and the west played out in the 1980s and 1990s,
the Shah’s eldest son and claimant to the dormant
title of Shah, Reza Pahlavi, decided to move to
the United States after first living in Egypt
and Morocco for several years after his father’s
death. He had become a fulcrum for conspiracies
concerning the Iranian regime. For instance,
in the 1980s he was in contact with the Israeli
government and elements in Saudi Arabia, which
is opposed to Shiite Iran on religious grounds
and because it views it as a regional rival.
By the end of the 1980s, Pahlavi was presenting
himself as the voice of the Iranian opposition in
exile and a leader of the Iranian American
community, which grew considerably in the
1980s as a result of the exodus following the
Revolution. As protests within Iran generated
national attention from 2009 onwards, Pahlavi
became more prominent, especially during the
US-Israeli attacks on Iran in June 2025 and
the spring of 2026. For instance, following
the killing of Ayatollah Khamenei on the 28th of
February 2026 there was speculation that Pahlavi
could become involved in forming a new government
in Iran. However, opinion polls and studies over
the years have consistently demonstrated that
while Pahlavi might be well liked amongst the
exile community, the Shah’s son lacks the kind
of internal support base within Iran that could
translate into a restoration of the monarchy
some day in the future, though he clearly
aspires to a leadership role of some kind.
The Shah of Iran’s legacy is complicated. He
was a man who came to power under difficult
circumstances, who often tested his relationship
with the western powers, yet managed to retain
their support, and who is today viewed, somewhat
paradoxically, as both a modernising reformer and
also an authoritarian. All of these things can be
true at the same time. The Shah’s rise to power
in succession to his father occurred because of
the unusual position Iran was in during the Second
World War and the desire of both the Germans and
the Allies to acquire control over the country and
its vital oil supply. In the aftermath of the war,
the Shah was able to retain the support of the
United States in the context of the Cold War,
even after Iran nationalised the Anglo-Iranian
Oil Company, an inflammatory action so far
as Britain was concerned. The simple reality
was that his actions were tolerated when set
against the backdrop of the Cold War, the rise
of socialist pan-Arab states in the Middle East
and the fact that his regime was one of the few
ones in the entire region that was not bitterly
opposed to Israel. He also did initiate reforms
that improved life in Iran for a lot of people
such as increasing literacy levels and he was
also responsible for a period of huge economic
growth. The country also became the most liberal
in the Middle East. People in countries like Saudi
Arabia, Qatar and the United Arab Emirates did not
enjoy anything near the liberties that Iranians
did in the 1970s. Moreover, with oil prices
turbocharging Iran’s economic growth from late
1973 onwards, the Shah should have been popular
and successful. His failing was in developing an
overly authoritarian method of ruling and engaging
in rampant corruption and financial mismanagement,
along with completely misjudging the political
atmosphere in the 1970s. Then again, maybe this
challenge was beyond the ability of any leader.
The same forces of liberalism and conservatism, of
secularism and religious zealotry, which the Shah
failed to contain in the 1970s, have characterised
Iran’s turbulent politics ever since.
What do you think of the Shah? Was he a liberal
ruler who was building a secular, modern Iran
before the Revolution led to his overthrow,
or was he a corrupt authoritarian who caused the
Revolution through his abuses of power? Please
let us know in the comment section, and in the
meantime, thank you very much for watching.